Rokan FARUQUI

I am a passionate software engineer. I have 5⁺ years of experience in building scaleable, secure backed applications for large organisations using .Net, Ruby and frontends using Angular and mobile applications using Xamarin and Ionic. I have been working as a remote software engineer on contract with a geographically diverse team and collaborated using Git, Azure, Bitbucket. I am proficient in object-oriented programming paradigm (Python, C#, Ruby). I also have training on Machine Learning and Data Analysis. I have solid understanding of basic algorithms-data structures, software development methodologies, version control systems, continuous integrations, and production level deployment.

PERSONAL DATA

PLACE OF BIRTH: Chittagong, Bangladesh

PRESENT ADDRESS: Department of Computer Science and Engineering,

University of Chittagong, Chittagong, Bangladesh

PHONE: +88-01738-857061
WHATSAPP: +88-01738-857061
EMAIL: rufaruqui@gmail.com

WEB: www.linkedin.com/in/rufaruqui/

WORK EXPERIENCE

So Xn

Software Engineer

XpertSolvers (*xpertsolvers.com*)

Dhaka, Bangladesh



Associate Professor

Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering)

University of Chittagong, Bangladesh



Research Assistant

Dept. of Computing and Software

McMaster University, ON, Canada



Software Engineer (NSERC IPS INTERN)

Palamino Inc (palominosys.com)

ON, Canada



Software Engineer (NSERC IPS INTERN)

Palamino Inc (palominosys.com)

ON, Canada



Research Assistant

Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering

St. Francis Xavier University, NS, Canada



Lecturer

Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering)
University of Chittagong, Bangladesh

2006 - 2009

2017 - Present

2017 - Present

2013-2016

Dec'11-Feb'12

Iun'10-'10

2009-2021

EDUCATION



PhD in *Computer Science (incomplete)* **McMaster Unversity**

2013 - 2016

Hamilton, ON, Canada



MS in *Computer Science*St. Francis Xavier University
Antigonish, NS, Canada

2009 - 2012



BEng in Computer Science & Engineering

2001 - 2005

Chittagong University of Engineering and Technology Chittagong, Bangladesh

LICENSES & CERTIFICATIONS



Google Cloud Big Data and Machine Learning Fundamentals

Issuing authority: Google Cloud Training

Issued on October 2021.

Credential ID: Y54JNRVYDNQQ



Introduction to TensorFlow for Artificial Intelligence,

Machine Learning, and Deep Learning Issuing authority: DeepLearning.Al

Issued on October 2021.

Credential ID: CB94H8YGBFBQ



Teaching and Learning Foundations

Issuing authority: MIIETL, McMaster University

Issued on August 2016.

PROFESSIONAL TRAINING AND WORKSHOPS

Machine Learning

SciTinyML: Scientific Use of Machine Learning on Low-Power Devices, International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP), Trieste, Italy, 2021.

Data Analysis

Joint ICTP-IAEA School on LoRa Enabled Radiation and Environmental Monitoring Sensors, International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP), Trieste, Italy, 2018.

Wireless Networking

ICTP-ITU School on New Perspectives on Wireless Networking, International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP), Trieste, Italy, 2008.

HONORS AND AWARDS

Sep'16 - Aug'17	International Excellence Award, McMaster University, Canada - \$5,000/year
Sep'15 - Aug'16	International Excellence Award, McMaster University, Canada - \$5,000/year
Feb'10 - Jan'12	NSERC Industrial Postgraduate Scholarship (IPS 1), Canada - \$21,000/year
2001-2004	Merit Scholarship [for all semesters], Chittagong University of Engineering and Technology, Bangladesh

FEATURED PROJECTS

.Net, Xamarin	ArcGIS based mobile application to manege natural resources , Think4F, USA.
Ruby, Postgres	Data Migration Tool, Australia.
Ruby on Rails, Linux	Report Mailer, Summit Alliance Port Limited, Bangladesh.
.Net, Angular	An Off-Dock Management System. ERP Solutions, Summit Alliance Port Limited, Bangladesh.

PUBLICATIONS

2021	Abdur Rakib, Rokan Uddin Faruqui , Model checking ontology driven reasoning agents
	using strategy and abstraction, Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experi-
	ence, e5205.

- Rokan Uddin Faruqui, Modelling and Verifying Dynamic Access Control Policies in Workflow-Based Healthcare Systems, Jurnal Kejuruteraan 32 (1), 1-7.
- Rokan Uddin Faruqui and Wendy MacCaull: OwlOntDB: A Scalable Reasoning System for OWL 2 RL Ontologies. In International Symposium on Foundations of Health Information Engineering and Systems (FHIES 2012) co-located with FM 2012, Revised Selected Papers, LNCS Vol 7789, pages 105-123, Springer.
- Abdur Rakib, **Rokan Uddin Faruqui**, Wendy MacCaull, *Verifying resource requirements for ontology driven rule-based agents*. In 7th International Symposium on Foundations of Information and Knowledge Systems (**FolkS 2012**) Kiel, Germany, **LNCS** Vol. 7153, pages 312-331, Springer.

TALKS

June 20-22, 2013	Fazle Rabbi, Wendy MacCaull, Rokan Uddin Faruqui: A scalable ontology reasoner via incremental materialization. In CBMS 2013, Porto, Portugal.
March 5-9, 2012	Abdur Rakib, Rokan Uddin Faruqui, Wendy MacCaull: Verifying resource requirements for ontology driven rule-based agents. In FolKS 20112, Kiel, Germany, .
May 20, 2012	Wendy MacCaull, <u>Fazle Rabbi</u> and <u>Rokan Uddin Faruqui</u> : Next Generation Workflow and Data Management Tools with Application to Health Services Delivery, National Research Council, Fredericton, Canada .
May 04, 2012	Rokan Uddin Faruqui and Wendy MacCaull: Scalable Reasoning over OWL 2 RL Ontologies. 4th Atlantic Workshop on Semantics and Services (AWoSS 2012), Halifax, NS, Canada.

LANGUAGES

BENGALI: Mothertongue ENGLISH: Working Proficiency ARABIC: Basic Knowledge